Welcome to yet another week in AI and
this one was particularly interesting
and a lot of things were released that
will have a large impact in the future
and I think you should know about it
now. I'm talking about native app
integrations in ChachiT in a way that we
haven't seen before. OpenAI releasing an
agent builder and updates to how Sora
handles copyright and an update to Sora
and so much more in this week's episode
of AI News. You can use the show that
pulls together all the AI releases of
this week. And we filter by the ones
that are available and useful right now.
And the lead story oh so clearly this
week is everything that OpenAI released
during their dev day this week. And I
think two things really stand out here
and I want to dedicate separate segments
to them. First of all, apps inside of
chat GPT and the SDK that comes along
with it. And secondly, the open AI agent
builder. Let's start with the chat GBT
piece as this is a familiar environment
for most of the viewers and frankly most
people in the western world. I mean it
has over 800 million active users. And
rather than me telling you about this,
let me show you because they've released
apps in various forms over the past few
years, namely GPTs and the plug-in
store. And then they also had
connectors. But this is different from
all that. It's available now in the US
and they noted later it's coming to the
rest of the world. But right now, me
being on this VPN, I can head on over to
my settings, go to apps and connectors
that up here you can see the connected
apps. And this is what's new. These
apps, these connectors were there
before. But what really changed now is
these applications. And now you might be
asking like, hey Eigor, didn't we
already see this? Don't we already have
connectors? Didn't they try plugins
before? And then the GPT store kind of
did the same thing with actions. And you
would be right. It looks very similar on
the surface, but a few details are very
different. And I think the details
really, really matter here. So I think
the closest comparison we can draw here
are the plugins that launched in early
2023, I believe. And and I believe they
were phased out like half a year later.
It was some of the similar applications
that now shipped under this apps title.
Booking, Expedia, Canva, all the usual
suspects, but the plugins completely
flopped. As I said, they literally
removed it from chatb. That doesn't
happen often and I think the reason for
that was that the functionality was not
that deep. Often the plugins used to
just display results from within the app
in chat and then you still had to head
out. Plus, and I think this is the
detail that really really matters. You
had to enable the plug-in before
actually using it. Whereas these apps,
if you enable them, chat makes its own
decision on when they should be
activated. So, for example, let's go
through the process of connecting Canva.
Right here, I happen to have a paid
Canva account. me activating this for
the first time, I have to log in to
authorize the app. That makes perfect
sense. And now that it's authorized,
you'll see it appear under my active
apps. And now if I go into a new chat
and say something like create a
presentation with Canva for my AI news,
you can use show that compares Google
versus chat GBT. And here I explicitly
mention Canva. So it should use that app
to actually invoke it. And as you can
see immediately, it access my Canva
account. And here's the interesting
part. It starts doing the work right
here in CHBT. But these are the two
biggest changes here and I think they
matter. First of all, I don't have to
enable the plug-in once the app is on.
It just works. And secondly, it does the
work inside of Chat GPT and I don't have
to leave. It actually created multiple
presentation drafts for me. Let's just
say I like this very first one here. I
can open it up and the whole
presentation is right here. Again, I'm
still inside of Chat GPT. Now, I could
follow up and edit it and say something
like the first one is great. Change
title to the information rivalry. And
then it should adjust this one
accordingly. I didn't even read the
whole thing. It asks me, would you like
me to go ahead and update the title
slide? So, let's just say make the edit.
Okay, so it made the edits. Would you
like me to commit the changes to the
presentation? Of course. Okay, so let's
have a look inside of Canva now. Yeah,
and there it is. So, it can edit that
way. So, this is a new way to work and
it's probably not going to be perfect as
of now, but intuitively, I really think
and feel that this just makes sense.
Working inside of Chat GPT rather than
it being this bridge to all these other
apps is what you want to do. Now, I
really want to show you one more
example, and that's a Spotify related
one, cuz that works in a different way,
and I genuinely love it. But before I do
that, I want to give you a few more
details here because these apps are
limited as of now. As you can see,
there's five of them right now in their
blog post and they have a bunch of
partners that are coming soon. But the
vision here is what matters because
along with these partnered apps, they
also released the apps SDK where
developers can actually build their own
apps and integrate them into Chat GPT.
And then the vision is to eventually
launch something like an app store in
chat where you just activate all these
various apps and all of a sudden we move
away from this model where on your phone
you need to select applications to do
things. Chat GPT will hopefully do that
for you. But I really want to highlight
this last paragraph here that says
what's next for these apps in chat GPT.
So, as I said, developers will be able
to open submissions to publish their
apps inside of chatbt and then if they
meet OpenAI standards, they will be
listed and they will also share details
on monetization soon with a new agentic
commerce protocol. One side note is that
the agents SDK actually uses the open
MCP standard. So, a lot of the existing
MCP servers that exist will just plug
into this. So, essentially people will
be able to build their own apps. But for
now, we're limited with these. And now I
want to show you the second example
which is Spotify. Because you could see
something simple like create a work
playlist with Studio Ghibli music. Hit
enter. And now you should engage the
Spotify app without me telling it cuz
hey that's where I do my playlist right?
And in no time at all it loads various
tracks and Spotify creates a custom
playlist in your account. I did connect
the app in advance but you have to do it
once. And voila. If I click the playlist
it opens it up. And there we are. A
wonderful custom playlist that I could
now keep editing inside of Chetch. So if
I follow up with something like mix in
Lord of the Rings film music, Chacht is
actively editing the playlist for me
that will then show up across all my
devices without me ever leaving Chacht.
I could just open the playlist and
that's it right there. Once stuff
integrates like this, it sort of just
works. But the real power of this will
become evident once you get multiple
applications that you use regularly
involved inside of Chat GPT and then
time will show if people actually use
it. Okay, let's see what's next. Okay,
so real quick, I'm going to show you a
platform that we've always used to teach
and execute automations internally at
the AI Advantage, and that is Make, the
platform that lets you automate just
about anything under the sun. And also,
big thank you to Make for sponsoring
this video and making our productions
possible. They really are the perfect
partner for us to work with because we
actually use Make all the time. If
you're not familiar, it's a visual
orchestration platform that lets both
individuals and teams accelerate and
scale with AI. With a combination of
make and AI tools, you can orchestrate
things visually. You can build and scale
up agentic automations, monitor
everything in real time, quickly, gather
insights, and implement the right
changes. But ever since we started using
Make, the platform has developed a lot
because they've added a ton of useful
features and updates. Two of my personal
favorites they added recently are the AI
agents and the grid view. So, first up,
AI agents. If you're watching this
channel, you might be familiar with that
concept. And in the context of make,
they're basically a dynamic way to
adjust a workflow autonomously without
relying on a specific rule that routes
the automation the same way every single
time. The decision-m becomes more fluid
and intelligent through the use of AI
tools by plugging LLMs into the middle.
And because Make is a visual first AI
assisted low code platform with over
2,500 pre-built applications, you can
automate things away quickly without
getting caught up in custom development
work. So these AI agents in make pair
nicely with their new grid view tool.
This is basically a new way to view
automations and also edit them. Grid
view shows you a realtime interactive
overview of your entire AI and
automation landscape and you can easily
monitor in real time. It also makes it
way easier to find bottlenecks in your
automations. So you can remove them or
troubleshoot issues all from one place
which allows you to scale with control
using make grid mcps and analytics. So,
if you want to start creating
intelligent agentic automations, sign up
for make today with the link at the top
of the video's description. New users
will receive one month for free on the
pro plan. And that plan includes 10,000
operations per month amongst other
perks. All right, now let's have a look
at the next piece of AI news that you
can use. And this next story really
shook up the entire startup space in AI
because they shipped their very own no
code interface that directly competes
with well, I would say most AI startups
out there these days. And look, overall,
we're not going to be doing a deep dive
on this tool. I just want to show you
that if you go to
platform.open.com/agent-builder,
well, they now too have a automation
builder. But I think again, just like
with the apps, this is a case of, hey,
they ship their own product, but they're
nowhere close to the depth of some of
the other tools that have been at this
for years. I think this is serious
competition, but other tools, even like
make, who sponsored today's video, it's
just not even close in terms of all the
integrations and documentation and
options you have in some of these
competing tools. Whereas this agent
builder has a lot of things you need, a
lot of the essentials, but there's some
major major limitations. One of them is
that if you want all these integrations,
well, there needs to be an MCP for them.
So, you can add these MCP nodes here in
the middle and then you could connect up
the either one of the MCPS here or you
could do a custom one right here. But
the beauty of using something like make
or one of the other products is that the
connections are all just there. You just
log in via OOTH and you don't need to be
using the MCP server. Everything that
you see here and all of these notes,
they're really robust. But I do have to
point out the limitations here where
another one is that you're strictly
limited to OpenAI models obviously
whereas with these other tools you can
use any models for example I myself love
to use claude for writing not possible
here which might be okay it's just
something to be aware of but yeah other
than that classic automation tool which
could also be double the agent builder
there's a trigger here there's actions
here conditions in the middle and when
you add these agentic nodes it basically
lets you add instructions you can use
one of the open AI models so as we'll
talk about in a second we could for
example use GPD5 Pro here. Now you could
add tools to the agent via the MCP
servers and then there's more
customization but that is kind of the
gist of it. If you want to learn more
about this the documentation is really
the place to do that and they also
shipped the chat interface along with
that. So now it's really easy to create
a chat interface to engage these
workflows. Just like the apps I feel
like this is the same story. This
release kind of echoes the same theme as
in like this is a earthquake that
happened but it might take weeks or even
months to see if this produces a tsunami
that hits the shores. As of right now
it's a nice development and we should
definitely know about it and start using
this stuff but I don't think this is a
complete gamecher as of today. But again
these are def focused releases and
people have to start building on top of
this for it to really matter. Okay. And
there's one more big OpenAI related
story that we have to cover and that are
the changes to Sora. I'll keep this
rather brief. There's really three
bullet points I want to hit here. The
first one is that they shipped an API.
So at 10 cents per second, you can now
generate Sora 2 videos through the API.
I did the quick math. A future length
movie would therefore cost around $700.
Fair enough. Like just to be clear,
that's what it would cost to generate
it. You're not going to get a movie out
of just one prompt. But if you just
accept the first generation, that's what
it would cost. Secondly, they updated
the moderation policies. So you might
have noticed that on Sora 2 release, you
could just use everything. All the
different IPs were in there. you could
essentially generate most shows and
historic characters, celebrities, all
that, no problem. Now, they're starting
to reel that back. And Sam Alman
published this blog post where they said
that, hey, this is a new category.
They're learning. They're making changes
quickly. They're giving the rights
holders more control over the generation
of characters, and they're going to
introduce a way to make money for video
generation. This is still very vague,
but in the end, he said this. Please
expect a very high rate of change from
us. We plan to do our iteration on
different approaches in Sora. So the
product is going to evolve, change,
they're going to test things just like
they are in chat GPT with the apps now
for example and then only time will show
where this will land eventually. But the
virality that this caused is definitely
an indicator that the category of AI
generated video for entertainment is
just a thing from here on out forever
now. And the first related thing that I
wanted to tell you about is just a
simple GitHub repo from Matt Schumer
Sora extend where you can take clips and
artificially extend them when you're
calling the API. So you could create
clips that are longer than the time
limitation in Sora 2. And that's a Sora
related updates this week that you
should know about. And amongst all of
those open eye releases, there were even
more, but I think it's enough if we kind
of just list these others rather than
going into detail. So first of all, they
made GPT5 codecs widely available now.
So it's not in research preview anymore.
If you're not familiar, that's the
coding specific model. And they added a
few new things like a native Slack
integration or again an entire SDK where
people can just build really efficiently
with the model. Then also GPT5 Pro is
now available for the API. And I think
this is significant. I don't know where,
but for me personally, GPT5 Pro is the
go-to model if I really care about a
question. It's gated behind the $200 CHD
Pro plan, but now you can make API
calls, which are pricey, directly to the
call and just pay for what you use. They
also shipped a smaller voice model, GPT
Realtime Mini. It's 70% cheaper than the
advanced voice mode. And that's pretty
much all from their dev day. Next up, we
have a short story, but one that
nevertheless I think you should know
about, and that is the fact that there's
a new top contender for best image
generator out of China. It's fully open
source, a very large one. So, you won't
be able to run this locally, but Hanuan
image 3.0 didn't just surprise me, but
also everybody in our community. This
open-source model placed at the top
level along with Midjourney, Gemini, and
even beats out some of the other Chinese
models. And this isn't just kind of a
personal take. In Elmarina's text to
image rankings that actually got first
spot, but rather than talking about it,
as per usual, we'll just show you some
example images. I think this one
actually excels across all categories. I
mean, the logo looks really great, the
pictures look detailed, but not too
detailed, the graphics look great, and
especially this comic when compared to
some of the other image generators came
out super well. And the thing is fully
open source. So, you know, we get all of
these big stories out of the US and
OpenAI, but China is not stopping.
They're just pursuing a different
strategy, which is a very open-source
focused one. Perplexes comet being
available to everybody for free. If
you're not familiar, that's their AI
powered browser. And up until now, you
had to pay $200 and have an invite code
to access this and now it's just there.
But honestly, with Next Quick Hit from
Gemini and what Claude did with their
browser extension, I think Comet just
doesn't perform as solidly as some of
the competition here. So, even though
this might be free and you can try it
now really easily, I'm not sure it's
worth your time. But hey, I know a lot
of people use it. So, leave a comment if
you have something specific where it's
better than cloud browser extension. I
haven't found an example like that yet,
but happy to learn. And the next story
sort of ties into this because Gemini
2.5 computer use came out and it's a new
computer use model and you can actually
really easily test this if you head on
over to gemini.browserbase.com.
They hosted a version of it and what you
can essentially do is give it a task and
inside of this virtual machine it's just
going to perform it. The benchmarks on
this model look really impressive. But I
think this integration where it's in a
standalone computer rather than in your
browser is just inferior. At least for
me it is because doesn't have all the
login credentials. It's going to lose
the cookies. It's just cumbersome. Look,
even now if I gave it this basic task, I
need to kind of go down and accept these
cookies so it can proceed. But if you've
never experienced one of these computer
use models, this is your opportunity.
You can just go to this link, give it a
task, and see what it does on this site.
It has never been easier. Half a year
ago, you needed to run it through Docker
and install a bunch of stuff. Now, it's
just you go to a link and give it a
task. And this sort of works. Although,
I do think that the Chrome extension is
superior just because it has everything
that your browser has, and that's what
you care about. But you can see it
working here. And it's a great thing to
play around with if you haven't explored
this category of AI at all yet. In this
week's quick hit section, it's just XI
introducing imagine v0.9. And you can
test it out right here. And it sort of
has this infinite scroll interface. So
if I just go ahead and say a cat with a
hat as I usually do, then it's just
going to generate a infinite amount of
cats with hats. If you keep scrolling
and if you just hit play on maybe this
wizard cat right here, it's going to
turn it into a video. The model is good,
but nothing special. They're just
throwing their hat into the ring. No pun
intended there. And this is what the
video looks like. That's fine. Then we
have also some updates to Google Opal
and this was a thing that I personally
found really interesting when it came
out. Google product that makes these no
code interfaces as simple as they could
be and they added a bunch of things to
this. So first of all it's globally
accessible before it was gated and you
needed a VPN. Now 50 new countries have
access and can play with this and they
added features that were really missing
like debugging. So if you want to get
into building these no code workflows, I
think this actually might be the best
entry point just cuz it's so damn simple
and completely free from Google and it's
available everywhere now. And there you
go. That's pretty much everything we
have for this week. I think a lot of
these releases, especially the OpenAI
ones, will need some time for people to
build on top of them. These are
developer focused releases, and as you
saw, the chat ship apps are very limited
for now with large plans for the future.
So, I think over time, these will be
really significant, but as of now, I
would mostly say it's a good moment to
learn about this stuff, to start
experimenting and using it, but the real
impact of this will only be seen over
time. All right, and with that being
said, my name is Igor, and I hope you
have a wonderful